<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Charlie Pauvert webpages - Visualisation</title><link href="https://cpauvert.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://cpauvert.github.io/feeds/visualisation.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://cpauvert.github.io/</id><updated>2021-06-09T09:34:23+02:00</updated><entry><title>mi-atlas: an interactive and evolving catalogue of microbial interactions</title><link href="https://cpauvert.github.io/mi-atlas-catalogue-of-microbial-interactions.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-06-09T09:34:23+02:00</published><updated>2021-06-09T09:34:23+02:00</updated><author><name>Charlie Pauvert</name></author><id>tag:cpauvert.github.io,2021-06-09:/mi-atlas-catalogue-of-microbial-interactions.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Checkout &lt;a href="https://cpauvert.github.io/mi-atlas"&gt;https://cpauvert.github.io/mi-atlas&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style="float: left; border-radius: 5px; margin: 10px; padding: 0;" width="173" height="200" src="https://cpauvert.github.io/images/logo-mi-atlas.png"&gt; A couple of weeks ago, I read an article by &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/femsle/fnz125"&gt;Pacheco and Segrè, 2019&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;em&gt;FEMS Microbiology Letters&lt;/em&gt; regarding microbial interactions and how to go beyond a classification dedicated to ecological outcomes only. Of course, no classification is perfect (just like standards will forever be developed to encompass exceptions, &lt;a href="https://xkcd.com/927"&gt;leading to even more standards&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They propose to encode interactions between microorganisms using several binary (&lt;code&gt;0/1&lt;/code&gt;) or ternary (&lt;code&gt;0/1/-1&lt;/code&gt;) &lt;em&gt;attributes&lt;/em&gt; to build a catalog amenable to quantitative analyses. I thought this was a good idea. But I was frustrated that their (huge) initial effort to describe 74 interactions was &amp;ldquo;buried&amp;rdquo; in the Supplementary Material section of their article. Such multivariate table with 33 columns, while suitable for machines is hard to encompass for human. So I started to work on how to improve the visualisation of the catalogue and provide means for others scientists to contribute easily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, I provided:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a &lt;a href="https://cpauvert.github.io/mi-atlas"&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a &lt;a href="https://cpauvert.shinyapps.io/mi-atlas"&gt;Shiny application&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and a one &lt;a href="https://github.com/cpauvert/mi-atlas"&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; repository to bring them all (&lt;em&gt;and in the darkness bind them&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://cpauvert.github.io/mi-atlas"&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; presents their framework and the idea behind my project. The &lt;a href="https://cpauvert.shinyapps.io/mi-atlas"&gt;Shiny application&lt;/a&gt; displays the catalogue, allows to interactively focus on one interaction and helps users to encode a new interaction within the framework.
Have a look and do not hesitate to &lt;a href="https://github.com/cpauvert/mi-atlas/blob/main/CONTRIBUTING.md"&gt;drop an issue&lt;/a&gt; if you feel like it!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Visualisation"></category></entry><entry><title>Interactive visualisation of the influences of philosophers</title><link href="https://cpauvert.github.io/interactive-visualisation-of-the-influences-of-philosophers.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-02-19T11:43:26+01:00</published><updated>2021-02-19T11:43:26+01:00</updated><author><name>Charlie Pauvert</name></author><id>tag:cpauvert.github.io,2021-02-19:/interactive-visualisation-of-the-influences-of-philosophers.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Checkout &lt;a href="https://cpauvert.shinyapps.io/in-phi-luence"&gt;https://cpauvert.shinyapps.io/in-phi-luence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last year, I started a data visualisation and aggregation project on my free time which I recently updated. Feel free to explore at &lt;a href="https://cpauvert.shinyapps.io/in-phi-luence"&gt;cpauvert.shinyapps.io/in-phi-luence&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project stemmed from a question of my partner regarding the schools of thoughts and influences of philosophers and next thing I knew I had opened R and had an excuse for a first Shiny application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Screenshot of the Shiny application" src="https://cpauvert.github.io/images/in-phi-luence_screenshot.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The screenshot just above illustrates the Shiny application &lt;em&gt;in-phi-luence&lt;/em&gt; displaying an interactive network of philosophers. Initially the sole data source of philosophers influences was &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org"&gt;The Free Encyclopedia Wikipedia (en)&lt;/a&gt; whom articles on philosophers of science were automatically scraped (R code available on &lt;a href="https://github.com/cpauvert/in-phi-luence"&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Few months after the initial draft version of the application, I stumble upon an interesting project, &lt;a href="https://www.inphoproject.org"&gt;The Internet Philosophy Ontology Project (InPho)&lt;/a&gt; which is a scholarly resource that compiles ontologies on philosophers and which are then made accessible through API or OWL files. Using the latter, I was able to fetch and concatenate monthly archives of the InPho ontologies to build a network. The R and Python code, and a Snakemake workflow are available on &lt;a href="https://github.com/cpauvert/in-phi-luence/inpho"&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another awesome resource, &lt;a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/"&gt;The Standford Encyclopedia of Philosophy&lt;/a&gt;, could have been used for a curated source of influences. However it did not provide any API to access its data nor flat files databases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the future I plan to compare the two networks (Wikipedia vs. InPho) and perhaps suggest missing influences to Wikipedia. Another interesting lines would be the analysis of the philosophers network using node-level metrics. The in and out degrees are already displayed in a n interactive table but I unexpectedly struggle to find a relevant metrics (among centrality measures or authority scores) so far but there is room for improvements. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Visualisation"></category></entry></feed>